Finding aid to the Josephine Adelaide Clark Papers CA.MS.00139
Smith College Archives
Josephine Adelaide Clark Papers
1876-1979
Smith College Archives
Clark, Josephine Adelaide, 1856-1929
CA.MS.00139
0.625 linear feet (2 containers)
A member of the second graduating class, Class of 1880, and Librarian at Smith College from 1907-19. Collection contains biographical material, correspondence, personal journals, photographs, and newspaper clippings.
Biographical / Historical
Josephine Adelaide Clark was born in Weston, Massachusetts on March 9, 1856 to John and Caroline (Derby) Clark. She came to Smith College in the fall of 1876 after teaching at Waltham High School following her graduation in 1873. Josephine was a member of the second graduating class from Smith, and earned her B.A. in 1880. After graduation she held numerous teaching jobs until her focus switched to library work in 1888, when she entered the library school at Columbia College in New York City. Josephine later became the assistant librarian at Gray Herbarium at Harvard University, where her knowledge and love of botany offered her great assistance. In September of 1891, she took the position of Botanical Bibliographer for the Division of Botany within the U.S. Department of Agriculture. Two years later she was appointed as the Assistant Librarian for the whole department, and in 1901 accepted the position of Head Librarian for the U.S. Department of Agriculture. In June of 1907, Josephine returned to Smith College where she served as Librarian until her resignation in 1919. She died of pneumonia on March 24, 1929 in her home in Claremont, CA.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes biographical materials, correspondence, personal journals, collections of photographs and newspaper clippings regarding Clark's education and career at Smith College and elsewhere.
Related Material
Class of 1880 Records
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Josephine Adelaide Clark Papers were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
Clark, Josephine Adelaide, 1856-1929
- Biographical Material, 1896-1979 (Box 716.1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, general, 1916-1919 (Box 716.1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to class, 1881-1896 (Box 716.1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to class, 1897-1914 (Box 716.1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence to class, 1915-1928 (Box 716.1, Folder 5)
- Journal, Aug. 1881-Aug. 1883 (Box 716.1, Folder 6)
- Journal-Charleston, SC, April-June 1884 (Box 716.1, Folder 7)
- Journal, Aug-Sept 1899; May-July 1899 (Box 716.1, Folder 8)
- Journal-European Trip, July-Sept 1904 (Box 716.1, Folder 9)
- Notebook, 1907-1919 (Box 716.1, Folder 10)
- Photographs, 1876-1963 (Box 716.1, Folder 11)
- Photograph Album-South Carolina, 1884 (Box 716.1, Folder 12)
- College Photograph Album (Box 717)